{"tossups": [{"question": "The last colonial mayor of New York City, David Matthews, was accused of kidnapping a politician with this surname who, alongside William Smith, Jr. and John Morin Scott, was part of \"The Triumvirate.\" The first governor of New Jersey had this surname, as did a man who drafted the Declaration of Independence alongside Jefferson, Franklin, Adams, and Sherman. That politician with this surname worked with Robert Fulton on the first steamboat from Clermont Manor. For ten points, give this surname of \"The Chancellor\" who negotiated the Louisiana Purchase as Minister to France.", "answer": "<b><u>Livingston</u></b> (accept Robert R(obert) <b><u>Livingston</u></b>; accept William <b><u>Livingston</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In a public lecture, this man erroneously called Mario Vargas Llosa [[YOH-sah]] a \"Colombian Nobel Laureate\" despite neither designation being correct. This man's wife, Marta Sahag\u00fan [sah-hah-GOON]], was outed for diverting public lottery funds to her private charity. This man, who called Donald Trump's proposed border wall a \"Racist Monument\" on Twitter, faced controversy for calling his opponent, Francisco Labastida, a \"crossdresser.\" The sixty-year dominance of the PRI party was broken by, for ten points, what winner of the 2000 Mexican presidential election and leader of the National Action Party?", "answer": "Vicente <b><u>Fox</u></b> Quesada", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "St. Lubinus names a vestigial chapel below the ground of a building in this city, a predecessor of which was destroyed by Danish pirates. Cnut the Great helped fund the construction of a building in this city overseen by Bishop Fulbert. Henry Adams wrote about a building in this city containing over 170 stained glass windows. That building in this city, south of Paris, contains an early instance of the Flamboyant style and the external use of flying buttresses. For ten points, name this French city which is home to a noted namesake Gothic cathedral which contains the Black Madonna.", "answer": "<b><u>Chartres</u></b> [[SHART-ruh]] (accept <b><u>Chartres</u></b> Cathedral; accept Cathedral of Our Lady of <b><u>Chartres</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {"question": "This event's instigator claimed, \u201cThe time is now, the fifth month when the rain falls.\u201d Contrary to myth, only the main hall was set aflame during this event, plans for which were announced at a <em>renga</em> poetry session. Mori Ranmaru dutifully carried out the instructions of one figure involved in this event, the instigator of which was killed while fleeing the Battle of Yamazaki. This event was carried out by Akechi Mitsuhide, who was subsequently defeated by Toyotomi Hideyoshi. For ten points, name this incident in which the first \"Great Unifier\" of Japan was killed.", "answer": "<b><u>Death</u></b> of <b><u>Oda</u><u>Nobunaga</u></b> (accept either underlined portion of the name; accept <b><u>Honnoji</u></b> Incident; or <b><u>Honno-ji</u></b> no Hen; accept <b><u>killing</u></b>, or <b><u>assassination</u></b>, or <b><u>suicide</u></b>, or <b><u>seppuku</u></b>, or <b><u>harakiri</u></b> in place of <b><u>death</u></b>; prompt on partial answers; Editor's Note: Though Oda's death was a suicide via seppuku, it is often considered an \"assassination\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This work notes that the arrival of refugees in Europe led to a \u201cgreat shock.\" \"Reflections on the Hungarian Revolution\u201d are included in the fourteenth chapter of this work, which is divided into essays including \u201cImperialism\u201d and \"Antisemitism.\u201d The central concept of this work is contrasted with despotism and tyranny in that the aforementioned systems limit terror to political dissidents only. For ten points, name this first major book by Hannah Arendt, which examines a form of government associated with Nazism and Stalinism.", "answer": "<em>The</em> <em><b><u>Origins of Totalitarianism</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "This pitcher had a perfect game in which the opposing pitcher, Bob Hendley, only allowed one hit. Nolan Ryan\u2019s 383-strikeout season surpassed the previous record held by this man, who made a decision that resulted in Don Drysdale pitching the opening game of the 1965 World Series. That event prompted a remark during a Heritage Month event in which Barack Obama noted his own inability to pitch. This man sat out the first game of that World Series in observance of Yom Kippur. For ten points, name this legendary left-handed pitcher for the Dodgers nicknamed \u201cSandy.\u201d", "answer": "Sandy <b><u>Koufax</u></b> (or Sanford <b><u>Koufax</u></b>; accept Sanford <b><u>Braun</u></b>)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "One figure at this battle was killed while slashing his sword and yelling, \u201cSurrender, you traitors!\u201d The Illinois Monument formed the basis of the National Park at this battlefield. Cheatham Hill was the site of a bloody charge led by George Thomas during this battle which was won by Joseph Johnston's forces who were set up around Rocky Face Ridge. Occurring during William Tecumseh Sherman\u2019s Atlanta campaign, this battle inspired the name of the first MLB commissioner. For ten points, name this Civil War battle fought around a namesake northern Georgia mountain.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Kennesaw Mountain</u></b> (prompt on \"Kennesaw\" Mountain Landis)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The orator of this speech claimed, \u201cNever has a lawyer had to practice his profession under such difficult conditions.\u201d This speech asks, \u201cWhat law and what justice?\u201d and notes that its speaker has been held in solitary confinement for a period of 76 days. Delivered in 1953, this oration's speaker was a member of the Orthodox Party and was charged for his part in a raid on the Moncada Barracks in an attempt to overthrow Fulgencio Batista. For ten points, name this speech by Fidel Castro claiming that future generations would forgive him.", "answer": "<b><u>History Will Absolve Me</u></b> speech (or La <b><u>historia me absolver\u00e1</u></b>; accept \"<b><u>History</u></b> <b><u>will definitely tell it all</u></b>\"; or \"<b><u>historia definitivamente va a revelar todo</u></b>\"; prompt on descriptions of Castro's 1953 speech)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "General Gilbert Diend\u00e9r\u00e9 led a failed 2015 coup in this country, where Christophe Dabir\u00e9 [[dah-bee-REH]] resigned as prime minister in December 2021. After January 2022, this country was led by members of the Patriotic Movement for Safeguard and Restoration, whose actions led to this country being suspended from ECOWAS. For ten points, name this West African country where President Roch Kabor\u00e9 of the People's Movement for Progress was ousted in a coup led by Colonel Paul-Henri Damiba in Ouagadougou.", "answer": "<b><u>Burkina Faso</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "In an epic poem involving members of this ethnic group, a cyclops-like figure named Goggle-Eye is born to a <em>peri</em> spirit and a human father. That work about this ethnic group focuses on a soothsayer and storyteller given a title translating to \u201cGrandfather.\u201d The <em>Book of</em> <em>Dede Korkut</em> is a work focusing on members of this ethnic group, which ruled an empire that produced the <em>Book of Government</em>. That book was written by the Persian vizier Nizam al-Mulk, who was employed by a member of this ethnic group named Alp Arslan. For ten points, name this ethnic group of the Oghuz and Seljuks.", "answer": "<b><u>Turk</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Turk</u></b>ic; or <b><u>Turk</u></b>ish; accept Oghuz <b><u>Turk</u></b>s; accept Seljuq <b><u>Turk</u></b>s)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man depicted a mass grave for tenement residents in his <em>The Trench in Potter's</em> <em>Field</em>. This activist documented street gangs in photos such as <em>Bandit's Roost</em>, collected in a popular book. A member of the \"Good Movement\" named Lawrence Veiller worked with this man to promote \u201cmodel tenements.\u201d Mulberry Street was a common setting for the best-known works of this man, who used cartridges and flash powder as part of a New York City muckracking effort. For ten points, name this photojournalist of <em>How the Other Half Lives</em>.", "answer": "Jacob (August) <b><u>Riis</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "During this event, one figure claimed, \"All day long, I will never cease to settle here, there, and everywhere\u201d and claimed that material wealth was reserved for the righteous. Lots were used to pick the <em>dikasts</em> during this event, in which the concept of <em>asebeia</em> [[ah-seh-BEE-ah]] was central. An inner <em>daimon</em> allegedly prevented the unethical activity of a figure in this event who compared himself to a gadfly. Following this event, its central figure drank hemlock. For ten points, name this event in which charges of \u201ccorrupting the youth\u201d were leveled against a Greek philosopher.", "answer": "<b><u>Trial</u></b> of <b><u>Socrates</u></b> (accept descriptive answers that also include information of the charges levelled against Socrates; do not accept or prompt on \u201cdeath of Socrates\u201d))", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "This city\u2019s Aplerbeck Hospital was a transfer point for mentally disabled individuals being sent to Hadamar to be euthanized in the T4 program. Up to 25,000 people were employed at the Westfalenh\u00fctte [[vest-FAH-len-hoo-tuh]] in this city, an industrial site that was among the key targets of an Allied bombing campaign. This was the largest city targeted in a campaign by Raymond Poincar\u00e9 [[pwahn-kah-REH]] to limit the coal and steel output of its central nation. For ten points, name this largest city in the Ruhr and site of a \u201cBorussia\u201d football team.", "answer": "<b><u>Dortmund</u></b> (accept <b><u>Tremonia</u></b>; accept <b><u>Duorpm</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Two years prior to this conflict, its parties signed a \u201cseven-point agreement\u201d which prohibited one side from searching civilian vehicles. Wasfi Tal was assassinated following this conflict, in which one side was allied with Pakistan\u2019s Muhammad Zia-ul-Haq. A strip of land near Zarqa was the site of a hijacking during this conflict involving the <em>fedayeen</em> of a group who relocated following Israel\u2019s acquisition of the West Bank. The forces of King Hussein won this year-long conflict against the PLO. For ten points, name this civil war primarily fought in Jordan.", "answer": "<b><u>Black September</u></b> (accept <b><u>Aylul Al-Aswad</u></b>; accept <b><u>Jordan</u></b>ian <b><u>Civil War</u></b> before \u201cJordan\u201d is mentioned and prompt after)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "A deity popularly worshipped in Palmyra who represented this thing was Malakbel. A Lithuanian feast worshiping this thing, under the name Saule, was converted into St. Jonas's Festival. The Quran chastises the subjects of the Queen of Sheba for worshipping this entity, one representation of which was given elevated status under Aurelian\u2019s reign. A barge was used every night by an Egyptian deity representing this entity. The title \u201cInvictus\u201d was given to a god representing this object in Rome. For ten points, Ra represented what heavenly entity?", "answer": "<b><u>Sun</u></b> (accept <b><u>Sol</u></b> before \u201csolar\u201d is mentioned)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "After one event, this man told Hamar Greenwood, \u201cYou had us dead beat. We could not have lasted another three weeks.\u201d This man ordered the killing of a group whose service in the Middle East inspired its name, the Cairo Gang. This man claimed to have \u201csigned [his] actual death warrant\u201d after negotiating what he believed was \"the freedom to achieve freedom\u201d with David Lloyd George. Arthur Griffin signed that treaty with this man the year before an incident in County Cork in 1922. For ten points, name this pro-treaty revolutionary who was assassinated during the Irish Civil War.", "answer": "Michael <b><u>Collins</u></b> (or M\u00edche\u00e1l \u00d3 <b><u>Coile\u00e1in</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The last scene this actor ever filmed is nicknamed the \u201cLast Supper,\u201d as it portrays him making a drunken speech alone at a table. While in New York, this actor landed roles on Broadway in plays such as <em>See the Jaguar</em> and <em>The Immoralist</em>. This actor remains the only person to receive two posthumous Academy Award acting nominations. With only three films to his credit, for ten points, what actor starred in <em>East of Eden</em>, <em>Rebel Without a Cause</em>, and <em>Giant</em> before dying at age 24?", "answer": "James <b><u>Dean</u></b> (or James Byron <b><u>Dean</u></b>)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "One leader of this empire donated a cloak, which had allegedly belonged to Muhammad, to the Kirka Sharif. This empire acquired land north of the Sutlej River after defeating Sadashiv Rao Bhau at the Third Battle of Panipat. A <em>loya jirga</em> coronated the founder of this empire, Ahmed Shah. This state conquered Mashad from the Afsharid Dynasty and sacked Mughal-era Delhi before withdrawing to the western side of the Indus. For ten points, name this eighteenth-century Middle Eastern power, ruled by the namesake Afghan dynasty.", "answer": "<b><u>Durrani</u></b> Empire (or <b><u>Durrani</u></b> Dynasty; accept <b><u>Sadozai</u></b> Kingdom; accept <b><u>Afghan</u> </b>Empire before \"Afghan\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Nilus of Sora supported attempts by this man to secularize land belonging to monasteries. A regulation on legal fees was among the centralizing reforms put forth by the Sudebnik passed during the reign of this man. Philotheus [[fee-loh-THEH-ooss]] wrote a letter to this man claiming that the domain he ruled was the Third Rome. This man faced Akhamat Khan at a battle known as the Great Stand on the Ugra River. In 1480, the Golden Horde was defeated by this man who led efforts to renovate the Kremlin. For ten points, name this Grand Prince of Moscow.", "answer": "<b><u>Ivan III</u></b> of Russia (accept <b><u>Ivan III</u></b> Vasilyevich; accept <b><u>Ivan the Great</u></b>; prompt on \u201cIvan\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>Though he was never Speaker, this politician served as Dean of the House of</u></b> <b><u>Representatives after Sam Rayburn. With Park Trammel, this politician named a bill</u></b> <b><u>that authorized the creation of new warships. Considered the \u201cFather of the Two-Ocean</u></b> <b><u>Navy,\" (+)</u> this politician had the rare honor of having an aircraft carrier named after him while he was still alive. A landmark in the Ellsworth Mountains is also named after this Georgia congressman and is the southernmost of the Seven (*) </b>Summits. For ten points, name this ally of William Halsey and namesake of the highest peak in Antarctica.", "answer": "Carl <b><u>Vinson</u></b> (accept <b><u>Vinson</u></b>\u2010Trammel Act; accept USS <em>Carl</em> <em><b><u>Vinson</u></b></em>; accept <b><u>Vinson</u> </b>Massif)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Historian Frank Tipton said of this man, \u201cWhat would have happened had his</u></b> <b><u>father died sooner or if he himself lived longer?\u201d This man asked, \u201cWhy did Bergmann</u></b> <b><u>put his finger in my throat?\u201d after the doctor misplaced a cannula during an operation.</u></b> <b><u>The Antisemitic (+)</u> Petition was denounced by this man as a \u201cshameful blot on our time.\u201d Married to the eldest child of Prince Albert (*) </b>and Queen Victoria, for ten points, what German emperor succeeded his father, William I, and had a reign of only 99 days in the Year of the Three Emperors?", "answer": "<b><u>Frederick III</u></b> (or <b><u>Friedrich III</u></b>; prompt on \u201cFritz\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A \u201cstruggle\u201d for one field between this thinker and Karl Popper was analyzed</u></b> <b><u>by Steve Fuller. In his book</u> </b><em><b><u>The Essential Tension</u></b></em><b><u>, this man analyzed several \u201cConcepts</u></b> <b><u>of Cause in the Development of Physics.\u201d This man is best-known for a work that notes</u></b> <b><u>how the process of \u201cpuzzle-solving\u201d (+)</u> is an integral portion of the \u201cnormal\u201d part of one field\u2019s development, which is punctuated by events like the Copernican Revolution. That book by this man put forth the idea of the (*) </b>\u201cparadigm shift.\" For ten points, name this U.S. philosopher who wrote <em>The Structure of Scientific Revolutions</em>.", "answer": "Thomas <b><u>Kuhn</u></b> (or Thomas Samuel <b><u>Kuhn</u></b>; accept <em><b><u>Kuhn</u></b> vs. Popper: The Struggle</em> <em>for the Soul of Science</em>)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "<b><u>A disruption of fuel supplies during this period led to Operation Drumstick,</u></b> <b><u>which was a plan for Her Majesty's Armed Forces to replace striking Lorry drivers. The</u></b> <b><u>headline \"Crisis? What Crisis?\" was employed by the newspaper</u> </b><em><b><u>The Sun</u></b></em><b><u> to mock the</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> Prime Minister during this political period. Near the end of this political era, James Callaghan lost a vote of no confidence by one vote, dissolving his cabinet. A Shakespearian (*) </b>phrase names, for ten points, what late 1970s period of British history characterized by strikes which paved the way for Thatcherism?", "answer": "<b><u>Winter of Discontent</u></b> (do not accept \"The Winter of Our Discontent\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man's forces were ordered to club the party of Piet [[PEET]] Retief's</u></b> <b><u>delegation to death and plunder his</u> </b><em><b><u>laagers</u></b></em><b><u> in an 1838 massacre. This man executed</u></b> <b><u>his chief advisor, Ndlela, by slow strangulation with a cow hide garment. Following (+)</u></b> <b>mass desertion at the Battle of Maqongqo [[mah-KOHNG-koh]], this ruler was overthrown by his Boer-backed brother, Mpande [[mah-PAHN-deh]]. Losing the Battle of Blood (*) </b>River, for ten points, who was this Zulu king who assassinated his half-brother, Shaka?", "answer": "<b><u>Dingane</u></b> (or <b><u>Dingane</u></b> ka Senzangakhona Zulu; accept <b><u>Dingaan</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A novel about an author\u2019s experiences at this location includes one character's</u></b> <b><u>attempt to identify the \u201cVeiled Lady.\"</u> </b><em><b><u>The Harbinger</u></b></em><b><u> was a publication run from this</u></b> <b><u>place that espoused the ideas of Charles Fourier [[foor-YEH]]. Originally a joint stock</u></b> <b><u>company, this place was founded by Sophia and (+)</u> George Ripley, the latter of whom was a Unitarian Minister. The </b><em><b>Blithedale Romance</b></em><b> was inspired by its author's experience at this place, which was closely associated with (*) </b>transcendentalism. Nathaniel Hawthorne was a founder of, for ten points, what experimental \"Farm\" in Massachusetts?", "answer": "<b><u>Brook</u></b> Farm (accept <b><u>Brook</u></b> Farm Institute of Agriculture and Education; or <b><u>Brook</u></b> Farm Association for Industry and Education)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In 2021, prison sentences handed out during this \"Operation\" were the subject</u></b> <b><u>of a called-for nullification by Judge Edson Fachin [[fah-KEEN]] due to presiding judge</u></b> <b><u>S\u00e9rgio Moro's bias during proceedings. This \"Operation,\" which takes its name from</u></b> <b><u>the service (+)</u> station where it was first uncovered, led to the tanking of President Dilma Rousseff's popularity due to her being on the board of the namesake oil company. A money laundering scheme within (*) </b>Petrobras was revealed in, for ten points, what \"Operation\" that led to the rise of Jair Bolsonaro?", "answer": "Operation <b><u>Car Wash</u></b> (accept Opera\u00e7\u00e3o <b><u>Lava Jato</u></b>; prompt on answers like \"Petrobras scandal\" before \"Petrobras\" is mentioned)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>This artist decorated the Duomo with a portrait of an English mercenary on</u></b> <b><u>horseback in</u> </b><em><b><u>Funerary Monument to Sir John Hawkwood</u></b></em><b><u>. Vasari noted how this artist</u></b> <b><u>stayed up late in an attempt to find an exact vanishing point, which he explored in his</u></b> <em><b><u>The Hunt in the Forest</u></b></em><b><u>. (+)</u> This artist depicted Micheletto da Cotignola [[koh-teen-OH-luh]] and Niccolo da Tolentino in a set of three paintings depicting a 1432 battle between Florentine and (*) </b>Sienese forces. For ten points, name this Renaissance artist of <em>The Battle of San Romano</em>.", "answer": "Paolo <b><u>Uccello</u></b> (accept Paolo <b><u>di Dono</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>P\u00e8re Louis Bazin [[bah-ZAHN]] recorded the death of this ruler, who was</u></b> <b><u>surprised in his sleep by conspirators at Quchan [[KOO-chahn]]. A form of artillery</u></b> <b><u>known as the</u> </b><em><b><u>zamburak</u></b></em><b><u> was employed at a victory for this man over Muhammad Shah.</u></b> <b><u>This man's tribe in Khorasan (+)</u> informed the name of his dynasty, the Afsharids. The Battle of Karnal was won by this man, who conducted a number of beheadings along the Yamuna River and took the Peacock Throne (*) </b>as loot during a campaign against the Mughals. For ten points, name this \u201cPersian Napoleon\u201d who sacked Delhi.", "answer": "<b><u>Nadir</u></b> Shah (accept <b><u>Nader</u></b> Qoli Beyg; accept <b><u>Tahm\u0101sp</u></b> Qoli Khan)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Carl Hines called for a requirement to replace a word in this song with the word</u></b> <b><u>\u201cpeople\u201d every time it is sung in a certain legislature. This song inspired the original</u></b> <b><u>working title of</u> </b><em><b><u>Gone with the Wind</u></b></em><b><u>, which was \u201cTote the Weary Load.\u201d Originally</u></b> <b><u>named after (+)</u> \u201cPoor Uncle Tom\u201d from Harriet Beecher Stowe\u2019s best-known novel, this song's lyrics may have been inspired by visits to the Federal Hill plantation. Naming a state park in Bardstown (*) </b>centered on Senator John Rowan's home, for ten points, what is this state song of a certain commonwealth?", "answer": "\"<b><u>My Old Kentucky Home</u></b>, Good-Night!\"", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Runic Stone 194 in Uppland recounts how this monarch gave a local jarl</u></b> <b><u>[[YARL]] named Alli a</u> </b><em><b><u>danegeld</u></b></em><b><u> following his conquest of a foreign land. Pope John XIX</u></b> <b><u>[[the nineteenth]] was sent a letter by this ruler in an effort to mediate a conflict</u></b> <b><u>between the Archbishops (+)</u> of Canterbury and Bremen. This man organized a mercenary force with 200 longships to depose Edmund Ironsides, king of England, culminating in this mans' successful Siege of London. The North-Sea (*) </b>Empire of the early 11th century was formed by, for ten points, which son of Sweyn [[SVEHN]] Forkbeard?", "answer": "<b><u>Cnut</u></b> the Great (accept <b><u>Canute</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>Milton Brooks, from the</u> </b><em><b><u>Detroit News</u></b></em><b><u>, was the first recipient of this award in</u></b> <b><u>1941 for his work on the Ford Strikers Riot. John Robinson and Don Ultang won this</u></b> <b><u>award for their work depicting a African-American college football player, Johnny</u></b> <b><u>Bright, being deliberately injured by (+)</u> Willbanks Smith, a white football player. Joe Rosenthal, from the Associated Press, received this award in 1945 for his work titled (*)</b> \u201cRaising the Flag on Iwo Jima.\u201d For ten points, what American accolade awards journalists for their images?", "answer": "<b><u>Pulitzer</u></b> Prize for <b><u>Photography</u></b> (prompt on partial answer)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}], "bonuses": []}